Register of the M. V. (Mikhail Vladimirovich) Rodzianko Papers, 1916-1923
Hoover Institution Archives
M. V. (Mikhail Vladimirovich) Rodzianko Papers,
1916-1923
27003
Rodzianko, M. V. (Mikhail Vladimirovich), 1859-1924.
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, and reports, relating to Russian efforts in World War I, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, and anti-Bolshevik movements. Includes letters and reports to Generals Vrangel' and Denikin.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives. An increment was added in 1927.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (1 reel).
Access Points
Vooruzhennye sily na IUgie Rossii.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Statesmen--Russia.; Denikin, Anton Ivanovich, 1872-1947.; Vrangel', Petr Nikolaevich, baron, 1878-1928.
Biographical Note
1859 Born on family estate, Ekaterinoslavskaia Guberniia, Russia. Is educated at Pazheskii Korpus (Corps des Pages)
1878-1882 Serves in Guards Cavalry regiment
1883-1885 Serves as justice of the peace (mirovoi sud'ia) in Ekaterinoslavskaia Guberniia
1886-1891 Serves as Marshal of the Nobility of Ekaterinoslavskaia Guberniia
1900-1906 Serves as Head of the Ekaterinoslav Provincial Judiciary (Ekaterinoslavskaia Zemskaia Uprava)
1905 Is a founding member of Octobrist Party (Soiuz 17 Octiabria)
1906-1907 Is elected to the Third and Fourth Duma and appointed memberof the Government Council (Gosudarstvennyi Sovet)
1911-1912 Is elected president of the Third and Fourth Duma
1917 Is instrumental in persuading Emperor Nicholas II to abdicate. After the February Revolution resigns from the government and joins anti-Bolshevik forces in the south of Russia
1920 Emigrates to Serbia
1924 Dies, Belgrade, Serbia
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE FILE, 1918-1923. (Box 1)
  Holograph drafts of letters and letters to the editor related to political matters. Also includes copies of correspondence with Ataman Petr Krasnov. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- WRITINGS, 1916-1923. (Box 1)
  Holograph drafts and typescript copies of reports and articles related to political matters. Arranged chronologically
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1918-1923
  - General. Letters to the editor. Holograph drafts
    - Monarkhicheskii Sovet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Obshchee Delo, 1920 (Folder 2)
    - Russkoe Delo, 1922 Sept., re Grand Duke Kirill Vladimirovich (Folder 3)
  - Antonii, Metropolitan of Kiev and Galich, 1921 (Folder 4)
  - Krasnov, Petr, Ataman. "O vysylke Atamanom P. N. Krasnovym - M. V. Rodzianki iz predelov Vsevelikago Voiska Donskogo", 1918. Correspondence between Ataman Petr Krasnov and Mikhail Rodzianko. Typescript copies (Folder 5)
  - Schopfer, Sidney, 1923, re Conradi and Polunin case (Folder 6)
- WRITINGS, 1916-1923
  - "Po povodu konferentsii v Genue", n.d. Holograph draft (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Untitled report re situation on Russian Front, 1916. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - Untitled report to Gen. Aleksei Denikin re situation in Ekaterinoslav, 1919 Sept.-Oct. Typescript (Folder 9)
  - "CHto delat' Rossii i russkim liudiam", 1920 May. Holograph draft in two notebooks. Also includes part of draft letter to General Petr Vrangel' (Folder 10)
  - "CHto nuzhno delat'", 1921. Holograph draft (Folder 11)
  - "Posdnee raskaianie", 1921. Holograph draft (Folder 12)
  - Untitled essay re Conradi and Polunin case, 1923. Holograph draft (Folder 13)